Margaret Alexander Marsh Papers, 1911-1984
Smith College Archives
Margaret Alexander Marsh Papers
1911-1984
Marsh, Margaret Alexander.
RG 42 UUID:afa37424-d1df-49e7-9e12-9849d2322502
13 boxes (6 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Papers are primarily related to her research and work as a faculty member and a Class Dean at Smith College. The focus of her research was international relations, particularly the social and economic consequences of twentieth century imperialism in Central and South America. Materials include research notes, photographs, journals, writings lecture notes, and correspondence from students.
Margaret Alexander Marsh was born Margaret Charlotte Alexander on August 22, 1893 in Brooklyn, New York. Her parents were George and Emily Carter Alexander. She attended the Manual Training High School in Brooklyn, New York, and competed a B.A. in 1914 and an M.A. in 1916, both at Smith College. Her masters thesis, "The Development of the Power of the State Executive, With Special Reference to the State of New York" was published in Smith College Studies in History, Volume Two, Number Three, April 1917. Marsh worked as a Reader in History and Government while she did her M.A. at Smith 1914-1916.
From 1916 to 1924 Marsh worked in New York City as the Executive Secretary of the American Association for International Conciliation, an affiliate of the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, and as Secretary of the International Relations Clubs, which was organized by the Institute of International Relations. In addition she worked as a specialist on American investments in Mexico for the Federal Council of Churches. She also took courses at the New School for Social Research and Columbia University. While on leave from the AAIC from 1920-1921, she studied at the London School of Economics, worked with the League of Nations in London, and spent six months with the Junior Red Cross in Albania. On August 6, 1924, she married Allison Wilson Marsh on the Island of Guernsy. Mr. Marsh was a member of the Class of 1913 at Amherst College and was a Professor of Physical Education there 1917-1958. During the 1924-1925 academic year, Margaret Marsh worked as a Reader at Amherst College for Professors Harry Elmer Barnes and Frank H. Hankins, both of the Economics Department. Barnes and Hankins were also on the faculty of the Sociology Department at Smith, Barnes from 1923-1930 and Hankins 1922-1946.
From 1925-1927, Marsh did research on economic and social conditions in Bolivia for the American Fund for Public Service. The AFPS funded studies on American expansion and investment with the goal of advancing human enlightenment and social justice. The result of her research was the book, The Bankers in Bolivia: A Study in American Foreign Investment, which was published by The Vanguard Press in 1928. This series was edited by Marsh's colleague, Harry Elmer Barnes. Marsh worked as secretary of the Freshmen course "Problems of Citizenship" at Dartmouth College September 1, 1927 until June 30, 1929.
Marsh joined the Department of Sociology and Anthropology at Smith College in 1929 and taught at Smith until her retirement in 1959. She was hired as an instructor and then made Assistant Professor in 1930, Associate Professor in 1940 and Professor in 1953. She was chairman of the department for three years, 1942/1943-1944/1945. Charles H. Page, Sociology Professor at Smith 1946-60, writes in his book, Fifty Years in the Sociological Enterprise: A Lucky Journey, "The eldest in years but young in spirit, and least troublesome among us, was one of Smith's finest teachers, Margaret Marsh, admired and held in affection by students and colleagues alike. Margaret's widely elected courses on 'The Expansion of Western Culture,' showpieces in the college's curriculum, were a successful synthesis of the anthropology of cultural change, the sociology of what was later called 'modernization,' and the economics of imperialism."
The focus of Marsh's research was international relations, particularly the social and economic consequences of twentieth century imperialism. Most of her work dealt with Central and South America, but she also did research in Russia, Japan, China, and Africa. Marsh published several articles on Latin America for The National Encyclopedia and National Year Book. In addition, she was a staff editor of the American Sociological Review in 1958. During her first sabbatical in the spring semester of 1936, Marsh did research in East Asia. While on sabbatical during the 1945-1946 academic year followed by a leave of absence during the fall of 1946, Marsh did research in Venezuela and Central America under a grant from the Rockefeller Foundation. This research resulted in her article "Monoculture and the Level of Living: An Hypothesis," which was published in Inter-American Economic Affairs, Vol. 1, no.1, June, 1947. She defined "monoculture" as the restriction of a national economy to one dominant export, such as oil from Venezuela or coffee from El Salvador. During her sabbatical in Central America and Venezuela, she did research on how monoculture effected the standard of living of different social classes. Marsh said the following at a Round Table on Imperialism and War at the Student Anti-War Conference at Smith College in 1934, "I do affirm that the demands of capitalist enterprise in terms of raw materials, markets and fields for surplus capital investment, cannot be satisfied ultimately in a nationalist world without war-that permanent peace is not compatible with an economic nationalism which has its roots in the capitalist system."
In addition to teaching, Marsh served as Class Dean for the classes of 1952 and 1957 and directed the Junior Year in Geneva program during the 1958-1959 academic year. She remarked to Frank Hankins, on being appointed Class Dean, "I feel as though I had charge of 500 Ellens," referring to her daughter, Ellen, born on August 2, 1932. Marsh was well-loved by her students as evidenced by the voluminous correspondence she received from them.
Marsh remained active after her retirement in 1959. Her entries in the Smith Alumnae Quarterly document her travels with her husband all over the world including, Egypt, Russia, Afghanistan, Iran, Nepal, Kashmir, Kenya, Tanzania, Uganda, Jordan, Portugal, Scotland. She studied Russian and other languages and continued to write on various topics. She also served as Treasurer of the Class of 1914. In the February 1968 issue of the Smith Alumnae Quarterly, she notes that "When in Amherst, our consciences are relieved slightly by joining the Sunday noon silent vigil for peace in Vietnam." Her husband Allison Marsh died in 1976 and she died on December 10, 1984 in Amherst, Massachusetts at the age of 91.
The Margaret Alexander Marsh Papers are 6 linear feet and 11/2 linear inches The material ranges in date from 1911- 1984 with the bulk of the material from 1940-1959. The papers are primarily related to her research and work as a faculty member and a Class Dean at Smith College. The focus of her research was international relations, particularly the social and economic consequences of twentieth century imperialism in Central and South America. The bulk of the collection is research notes, subject files, lecture notes (from her own education and as an instructor), and correspondence from students. In addition, there are photographs, syllabi, travel journals, and her own published and unpublished writing.
This collection is organized into nine series:
I. Biographical Material
II. Correspondence
III. Courses Taken
IV. Courses Taught
V. Research Notes And Card Files
VI. Smith College
VII. Subject Files
VIII. Writing And Speeches
IX. Photographs
Restricted Materials
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to researchers according to the regulations of the College Archives, with the exception of five linear inches of student correspondence, which is restricted. The bulk of this correspondence (covering 1960-83) is from Ellen Hauser, Class of 1960, and will be closed until 2022.
History of the Collection
The Margaret Alexander Marsh Papers were donated to the College Archives by Marsh's daughter, Ellen (Marsh) Schleicher, in 1996 and 1997.
Search Terms
Marsh, Margaret Alexander.; Smith College--Faculty.
Additional Information
Separated Material
Three files were removed from the collection. Two files on faculty shows, "Love Among Ruins" (1952) and "In Deep Water" (1957), were moved to 40. Faculty Shows. One file on her work as Treasurer of the Class of 1914 was transferred to the records of the Class of 1914 and is not open to researchers.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL 1926-1984, 2 linear in.
  This series is organized into three subseries: GENERAL, FAMILY, and DIARIES AND CALENDARS. There is a small amount of personal material in this series including clippings from the Smith Alumnae Quarterly on Marsh, a booklet on Marsh family history, and information on a cottage that Marsh and her husband owned in Wellfleet, MA. The diaries are related to her research travel and the calendars to her profession life at Smith.
  - General 1947, 1952, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Family
    - Allison W. Marsh 1958, 1976 (Box 1)
    - Ellen Marsh 1946, 1961, undated (Box 1)
    - Marsh Family History 1928, undated (Box 1)
    - Wellfleet, MA Land and Cottage 1937-1938, undated (Box 1)
  - Diaries and Calendars
    - Travel Diary, Bolivia 1926 (Box 1)
    - Travel Diary, Bolivia (Allison Marsh) 1926 (Box 1)
    - Notes and Journal, Venezuela 1946, undated (Box 1)
    - Smith College Calendar 1951 (Box 1)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE 1911-1983, 10 linear in.
  This series is organized into three subseries: GENERAL, FAMILY, and SMITH COLLEGE. The SMITH COLLEGE subseries is divided by Faculty and Staff and Students. The correspondence from students is organized into several categories in the following order: General, Class of 1952, Class of 1957, and Junior Year Abroad in Geneva. The correspondence from students in the JYA Geneva program is organized into three sections; General, Class of 1960 and non-Smith Students. The bulk of the correspondence covers 1940-1961 and is from students who Marsh worked with as a Class Dean or as the Resident Advisor for JYA Geneva. A small amount of student correspondence is restricted. The bulk of the restricted correspondence is from Ellen Hauser, Class of 1960, and will be closed until 2022. It cover 1960-1983 and is 2 linear inches. The subseries FAMILY contains correspondence to her husband and daughter from her research trips to Patzcuaro, Mexico and Venezuela. There is also correspondence in SERIES VII. SUBJECT FILES.
  - General
    - Coburn, John and Ruth undated (Box 1)
      [See also Subject File]
    - Littlejohn, William 1914 (Box 1)
    - Meiklejohn, Alexander 1923, 1944, undated (Box 1)
    - Venezuela and Monoculture Article 1946-1948, 1961, undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1923-1983, undated (Box 1)
  - Family
    - Alice Alexander 1911 (Box 1)
    - Patzcuaro, Mexico 1940, undated (Box 1)
    - Venezuela 1946, undated (Box 1)
  - Smith College Faculty and Staff
    - Blakeslee, Albert F. 1951 (Box 1)
    - Bryson, Gladys Eugenia 1952 (Box 1)
    - Davis, Herbert John 1945 (Box 1)
    - DeNood, Neal Breaule 1953 (Box 1)
    - Grierson, Margaret S. 1954 (Box 1)
    - Hankins, Frank 1944 (Box 1)
    - Hornbeak, Katherine Gee 1948 (Box 2)
    - Randall, Helen 1964 (Box 2)
    - Wright, Benjamin Fletcher 1948-1952 (Box 2)
  - Smith College Students
    - Miscellaneous
      - Meyendorff, Alexandra (Class of 1933) 1948? (Box 2)
      - O'Connor, Egan (Class of 1958) undated (Box 2)
      - Proctor, Carolyn J. (Class of 1950) 1949 (Box 2)
      - Wise, Molly (Class of 1962) 1964 (Box 2)
      - Unidentified 1952-1964, undated (Box 2)
    - Class of 1952
      - General 1952, 1967 (Box 2)
      - Parents of Students 1952 (Box 2)
      - Prosser, Alfred L., father of Martha Prosser undated (Box 2)
        [RESTRICTED until 2050]
      - Felstiner, Susan 1952 (Box 2)
      - Hamilton, Eleanor (Regarding) c1951 (Box 2)
        [RESTRICTED until 75 years after the death of individuals mentioned.]
      - Morrell, Martha 1953 (Box 2)
      - Pines, Joan undated (Box 2)
      - Simkute, Stefanija (Regarding) 1952 (Box 2)
      - Spencer, Dorothy undated (Box 2)
      - Waterman, Fran undated (Box 2)
      - West, Shirley 1953 (Box 2)
      - Wood, Barbara 1952 (Box 2)
      - Worcester, Laurie 1952, 1971, 1976, undated (Box 2)
    - Class of 1957
      - General 1956-1957, undated (Box 2)
      - Parents of Students 1957, undated (Box 2)
      - Anderson, Ann 1955 (Box 2)
      - Crawford, Cynthia 1955? (Box 2)
      - Crile, Ann undated (Box 2)
      - Crocker, Marion 1955 (Box 2)
      - Franklin, Elizabeth 1957 (Box 2)
      - Gorman, Marjory 1955? (Box 2)
      - Gottlieb, Sybil 1955 (Box 2)
      - Grant, Mary undated (Box 2)
      - Hackett, Josephine 1975, 1983 (Box 2)
      - Hawes, Harriet 1961, 1963, undated (Box 2)
      - Kuhlthau, Margaretta 1956 (Box 2)
      - Michel, Eda 1961-1972, undated (Box 2)
      - Perry, Ann 1955 (Box 2)
      - Schwerin, Mary undated (Box 2)
      - Simenas, Vida undated (Box 2)
      - Smith, Martha 1955? (Box 2)
      - Taylor, Mary Alice 1957 (Box 2)
      - Webber, Mary 1956 (Box 2)
      - Winn, Esther 1981 (Box 2)
    - Junior Year Abroad, Geneva
      - General 1947-1960, 1965, undated (Box 2)
      - Class of 1960
        - Bland, Frances 1961 (Box 2)
        - Bollengier, Berta undated (Box 2)
        - Brown, Betsy Jean 1961, 1964, undated (Box 2)
        - Brutcher, Constance 1962 (Box 2)
        - Day, Pamela 1960-1969, undated (Box 2)
        - Dunphy, Sara 1960 (Box 2)
        - Gardner, Joan (Jackie) 1961-1964 (Box 2)
        - Hauck, Anne-Marie undated (Box 2)
        - Hauser, Ellen 1960-1962, 1963-1969, 1973-1983, undated (Box 2)
          [RESTRICTED until 2022]
        - Karapinka, Orysia 1960-1962 (Box 2)
        - Koch, Barbara 1961, undated (Box 2)
        - Lambert, Elsa undated (Box 2)
        - Meyer, Marguerite 1960, 1962, undated (Box 2)
        - Newberry, Barbara 1960 (Box 2)
        - Newman, Sandra 1961-1962, undated (Box 2)
        - Pathy, Christine 1961-1962 (Box 2)
        - Stackpole, Beverly 1962-1964, undated (Box 2)
        - Strayer, Elizabeth 1961-1962, undated (Box 2)
        - Taylor, Cynthia 1960, undated (Box 2)
        - Varnick, Reet undated (Box 2)
        - Watson, Jeanne, (mother of Patricia Watson) 1958-1959 (Box 2)
    - JYA Geneva Students 1958-1959, Non Smith
      - Cumins, Gail undated (Box 2)
      - Greene, Gail 1958-1965 (Box 2)
      - Huff, Katherine 1959-1962, undated (Box 2)
      - Huff, Katherine, (and her Mother, Leona Huff) 1959 (Box 2)
      - Kemble, Sara 1963 (Box 2)
      - Martin, Elizabeth 1961 (Box 2)
      - Robertson, Dorothy 1961 (Box 2)
- SERIES III. COURSES TAKEN 1914-1916, 1955, 2 linear in.
  This series contains notes that Marsh took in her undergraduate and graduate courses at Smith College 1914-1916. The exception is one folder on an Education Course that she took at the Harvard Summer School in 1955.
  - Botany 1914 (Box 3)
  - Botany 1 Laboratory 1914 (Box 3)
  - Government 1914 -1915 (Box 3)
  - Government 1915 - 1916 (Box 3)
  - American Government 1915 (Box 3)
  - Unidentified 1915 (Box 3)
  - Reading List, Education Course, Harvard Summer School 1955 (Box 3)
- SERIES IV. COURSES TAUGHT 1924, 1930-1960, 7 linear in.
  All of the course material in this series is from courses taught at Smith College except for one folder on a course at Amherst College. The bulk of the material is lecture notes and syllabi.
  - Economics, Government, and Sociology 47a 1947-1948 (Box 3)
  - History and Social Science 295a 1963 (Box 3)
  - Social Science 192 1959-1960 (Box 3)
  - Sociology 11a 1942 (Box 3)
  - Sociology 26 1930-1956, undated (Box 3)
  - Sociology 34a-b 1950-1960 (Box 3)
  - Sociology 37b 1941-1957, undated (Box 3)
  - Sociology 40b 1957 (Box 4)
  - Sociology 320 a-b 1937-1938 (Box 4)
  - Sociology and Anthropology 11a-b 1959-1960 (Box 4)
  - Sociology and Anthropology 310a 1959-1960 (Box 4)
  - "Social and Economic Institutions in Amherst College" 1924 (Box 4)
  - Unidentified Lecture Notes 1929-1937 (Box 4)
- SERIES V. RESEARCH NOTES AND CARD FILES 1917-1922, 1954-1956, 1962, undated, 1 linear ft. and 9 linear in.
  This series contains card files of research notes organized by subject and unidentified research notes. In addition, there is one card file that lists the contacts Marsh used for her research on the petroleum industry in Central and South America for her article, "Monoculture and the Level of Living: An Hypothesis."
  - Bibliography on Popular Culture 1962 (Box 4)
  - Card file of research notes by subject (Box 5)
  - Card file of research notes by subject and card file of contacts for research on the petroleum industry. (Box 6)
  - Notes, American Association for International Conciliation? 1917-1922 (Box 6)
  - Notes, Unidentified 1917-1918 (Box 6)
  - Notes, Unidentified 1954-1956, undated (Box 7)
  - Notes, Unidentified undated (Box 7)
- SERIES VI. SMITH COLLEGE 1931-1961, undated, 4 linear in.
  This series is organized into three subseries: GENERAL, CLASS DEAN, and RESIDENT DIRECTOR, JUNIOR YEAR ABROAD, GENEVA. This series consists of general material related to Marsh's work at Smith College including meetings and speeches in her role as the Class Dean of the Classes of 1952 and 1957, a list of JYA Geneva students during the 1958-1959 academic year, and information on the Seven College Conference in 1955 and 1956.
  - General
    - Committee on Honors of the History Department (Regarding Eleanor Hauser) 1959? (Box 7)
    - Committee on a Four Course Plan 1944, undated (Box 7)
    - Hankins, Frank 1938, 1970 (Box 7)
    - Proposals for Interdepartmental Courses in the Social Sciences undated (Box 7)
    - Salary 1931-1964 (Box 7)
    - Seven College Conference 1955 (Box 7)
    - Seven College Conference 1956 (Box 7)
  - Class Dean
    - Class of 1952
      - General 1948-1952, undated (Box 7)
      - Class Meetings and Speeches 1948-1952 (Box 7)
      - Questionnaire and Results 1967 (Box 7)
    - Class of 1957
      - Ephemera 1953-1957, undated (Box 7)
      - Statistics and Speeches 1953-1957, undated (Box 7)
      - Junior Year Abroad 1955-1956, undated (Box 7)
  - Resident Director, JYA Geneva
    - General 1958-1959 (Box 7)
    - General, 1947, 1955-1961, undated (Box 7)
    - List of JYA Geneva Students 1958-1959 (Box 7)
    - Course Evaluations 1959 (Box 7)
- SERIES VII. SUBJECT FILES 1921-1969, undated, 1 linear ft. and 5 linear in.
  Most of the subject files are on countries. In addition there are subject files on topics such as population and individuals. They contain newspaper clippings, pamphlets, articles, advertisements, correspondence, syllabi, lecture notes and research notes. Most reprints of articles from journals were removed from the collection. A photocopy of the front cover with biographical information was left in place of each one. See also subject card files in SERIES V. RESEARCH NOTES AND CARD FILES.
  - Africa 1963 (Box 8)
  - Albania 1921-1932, undated (Box 8)
  - Angola to Ghana 1958 (Box 8)
  - Bolivia 1922-1944, undated (Box 8)
  - Bolivia 1923-1933, undated (Box 8)
  - Bolivia 1926-1928, undated (Box 8)
  - Bolivia, Trust Contract and Tejada Report 1923, 1931 (Box 8)
  - Caribbean Seminar 1931-1932, undated (Box 8)
  - China 1940-1960, undated (Box 8)
  - Coburn, John B., Dr., Articles 1965, 1969 (Box 8)
  - Conference on Economic Factors in International Relations 1923-1926 (Box 9)
  - Gruening, Ernest 1935, 1947 (Box 9)
  - Imperialism 1922-1944, undated (Box 9)
  - Japan 1941-1959 (Box 9)
  - Latin American Economy Proseminar 1924-1944, undated (Box 9)
  - Mexico, Democracy and Free Enterprise 1920s, 1930, 1951, undated (Box 9)
  - Patzcuaro, Mexico 1940-1941 (Box 9)
  - Monoculture undated (Box 10)
  - Pamphlets and Articles, Misc. 1920s-1930s, 1950, undated (Box 10)
  - Population 1940s, undated (Box 10)
  - Population Explosion 1952-1958, undated (Box 10)
  - Russia, Travel 1929, undated (Box 10)
  - Russia, Pamphlets 1927-1930, undated (Box 10)
  - Russia, Newspaper Clippings 1926-1933, undated (Box 10)
  - Sociology and Immigration, folder 1 1930-1931 (Box 10)
  - Sociology and Immigration, folder 2 1930-1931 (Box 11)
  - Venezuela, Mementos 1946 (Box 11)
  - Venezuela, Research 1940-1951, undated (Box 11)
- SERIES VIII. WRITING AND SPEECHES 1948-1973, undated, 1 linear in.
  This series contains published and unpublished writing and speeches. Speeches, writing, and correspondence related to her writing may also be found in SERIES VII. SUBJECT FILES filed by subject.
  - Book Reviews, published 1959-1960, undated (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous 1948, 1951, undated (Box 11)
  - "Petroleum Seed: An Answer to Venezuela's Colonial Economy" undated (Box 11)
  - "Monoculture in Latin America: Plan of Study" undated (Box 11)
  - "The Problem of Finding Faith" undated (Box 11)
  - Rough draft of article on Sylvia Plath and May Sarton 1973, undated (Box 11)
  - Smith Alumnae Quarterly Article 1972 (Box 11)
  - Speech given at the Roundtable on Imperialism and War at the Student Anti-War Conference at Smith 1934 (Box 11)
- SERIES IX. PHOTOGRAPHS 1914-1982, undated, 4.5 linear in.
  The bulk of the photographs are of unidentified classmates from Marsh's years as a student at Smith and photographs of her students and their families. In addition, there are photographs from her research trips.
  - Smith College
    - Angell, Norman, Sir undated (Box 11)
    - Margaret Alexander (Marsh) and classmates 1914, undated (Box 11)
    - Unidentified Women, Classmates/Residents of Hubbard House?
      - folder 1 circa 1914, undated (Box 11)
      - folder 2 circa 1914, undated (Box 11)
    - Marsh and Smith College faculty undated (Box 11)
    - Class of 1952 Who's Who
      - Students 1952, 1955-1956, undated (Box 12)
      - Children of Students 1959-1960, undated (Box 12)
      - Ellen Hauser (Bernstein) and Family 1967-1982, undated (Box 12)
    - Research related travel
      - Caribbean Seminar circa 1932 (Box 12)
      - Patzcuaro, Mexico 1940, undated (Box 12)
      - Venezuela 1944, undated (Box 12)
    - Unidentified undated (Box 12)
- RESTRICTED MATERIALS
  - Restricted Material from Boxes 1-12 (Box 13)